Finding Aid for Gray Panthers of Huron Valley Records, 1979-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gray Panthers of Huron Valley Records 1979-2008
Gray Panthers of Huron Valley.
4 linear feet
Ann Arbor, Michigan-based chapter of the Gray Panthers. Subject files pertaining to chapter activities; administrative files include annual reports, correspondence, and newsletters.
9826 Bj 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Gray Panthers of Huron Valley (Donor No. 8693 ) donated this record group in February 1998. Additional materials have been received from organization members, notably Ruth K. Graves (Donor No. 9855 ).
The record group is open for research.
Maggie Kuhn founded the Gray Panthers (initially named "The Consultation of Older and Younger Adults for Social Change") in 1970 when faced with mandatory retirement. Its members were committed to building an intergenerational organization and initially focused their energies on opposition to the Vietnam War and fighting mandatory retirement.
The Gray Panthers soon expanded their mission to take on a range of social injustices. Their goals included fighting ageism; fostering a positive concept of aging as growth; helping remove barriers between generations; and promoting social change that will serve the needs of all ages. To these ends, the Gray Panthers have rallied around issues such as nursing home abuse, health care reform, age bias in radio and television programming, rent control, and decent housing.
The grass-roots Gray Panther network tackles issues at the community level. These nationally-dispersed groups prioritize membership involvement to take on social issues. Tactics include educational programs, petition drives, demonstrations, legislative letter-writing blitzes, and rallies. Members often are also involved in coalition groups.
The Southeastern Michigan Gray Panthers (renamed the Gray Panthers of Huron Valley in 1983) was formed in February 1979 "to further the ideals of the national Gray Panthers." The nascent group stated it was primarily concerned with housing, transportation, and nursing homes. In subsequent years, the Gray Panthers of Huron Valley members also organized for a nuclear freeze and the preservation of Social Security and Medicare.
This record group documents the Gray Panthers of Huron Valley's activities and administration from 1979 to 2008.
Subjects:
Aged--Michigan--Political activities.; Gray Panthers.; Gray Panthers of Huron Valley.
Genre
Videotapes.
- Activities
  The Activities series reflects the broad range of issues around which the Gray Panthers of Huron Valley were active. The Newspaper Clippings folder includes more than two dozen news reports, interviews, and letters to the editor that testify to the organization's community presence. The Local Actions folder is complementary as it includes both lists and background about the group's efforts.
  The Gray Panthers of Huron Valley sponsored a Health Care Forum in 1987, which is comprehensively documented, from the event's planning to its execution. The organization's formal declaration about Social Security, as well as its subsequent resolutions on the matter, comprise the Social Security Task Force folder.
  - Announcements for newspapers (Box 1)
  - Associations with Local Organizations 1979-1985 (Box 1)
  - Health Care
    - Forum on Health Care 1987 (Box 1)
    - General 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - Kuhn Visit to Ann Arbor 1982 (Box 1)
  - Life Cycle: Intergenerational Art Show May 1981 (Box 1)
  - Local Actions 1979-1986 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1989-1997 (Box 1)
  - Peace Actions 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Publicity for Local Events 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Social Security Task Force, "The Survival of Social Security," 1983 (Box 1)
- Administration
  The Administration series traces the life of the group through its Annual Reports to the national office; these include information about its membership size, budget, work with coalitions, and priorities. The Correspondence and Newsletters folders also reflect the group's development and relationship to the national Gray Panthers.
  - Agenda 1995-1997 (Box 1)
  - Agenda of steering committee 2003-2008 (Box 1)
  - Alerts and other announcements from national office (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - Articles of Agreement and Policies 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - Convenor's record book 1995-1997 (Box 1)
    include agendas, minutes, programs, etc.
  - Correspondence
    - General 1980-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - General 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - National Gray Panthers 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - History of Gray Panther Movement 1970-1981 (Box 1)
  - Membership (letters to prospective members) (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Steering Committee 1995-2007 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - 2003-2007 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1980-2007 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1997 (Box 1)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - Published material from national office (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Videotapes
  The Videotapes series consists of VHS copies of local access television programs of Gray Panther meetings or on topics of interest to senior citizens.
  - Gray Panther presentations from Ann Arbor Community Access TV (VHS) 1996-2008
    - Avalon Housing: an Alternative to Homelessness with Carol McCabe undated (Box 2)
    - State Board of Education, Report by Kathy Stroudt undated (Box 2)
    - Are We There for Our Children?, with Carol Tice 11/2/1996 (Box 2)
    - Campaign Finance Reform, with Linda Teete 2/6/1999 (Box 2)
    - Impact of Welfare Reform on Single Mothers in Poverty, with Valerie Polakow & Peggy Kahn 3/6/1999 (Box 2)
    - Genetic Engineering-What's the Fuss? Do You Know What You're Eating?, with Martin Heller 10/2/1999 (Box 2)
    - WTO Summit in Seattle: Who are Making the Decisions & What Are They Neglecting 12/4/1999 (Box 2)
    - Health Care for All, Y2K Campaign 2/5/2000 (Box 2)
    - Making Progress Towards Clinic Health Care 6/3/2000 (Box 2)
    - Educators of Teachers Talk About School Vouchers, with Dr. Jerry Robbins and Dr. Michael Adonnizzio 9/9/2000 (Box 2)
    - Vouchers 10/7/2000 (Box 2)
    - Dr. Jerry Walden 12/2/2000 (Box 2)
    - SPAN Litigation Project: Prilosec 2001 (Box 2)
    - Affordable Housing 1/6/2001 (Box 2)
    - Newmarket 2/3/2001 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Campaign Finance Reform 3/3/2001 (Box 2)
    - Meeting of Electoral Process, with Lynn Rivers 5/5/2001 (Box 2)
    - How Is Health of Our Community 6/2/2001 (Box 2)
    - Election Reform, with Michael Traubott 1/5/2002 (Box 2)
    - Islam, with Ala Falik 2/2/2002 (Box 2)
    - Water, with Chris Kolb 4/6/2003 (Box 2)
    - Testing 5/3/2003 (Box 2)
    - Prescription Drugs 10/4/2003, 2 tapes (Box 2)
    - Book Reviews 3/6/2004 (Box 2)
    - Actionable Intelligence, with Marilyn Rosenthal 10/2/2004 (Box 2)
    - Education Update with Anthony A. Derezinski February 5, 2005, VHS and GX-MP cassettes (Box 2)
    - Health Care 5/6/2006 (Box 2)
    - Election Proposals 10/7/2006 (Box 2)
    - "Our Shadow Army: the Role of Military Contractors in Iraq and Elsewhere" May 5, 2007, VHS and GX-MP cassettes (Box 2)
    - MI Re-entry Program, with Mary King & Leslie Brown 5/3/2008 (Box 2)
  - Peace Insight program
    - "Top 10 Reasons for War in Iraq Refuted by Peace Lobbyist & Veteran. April 1 and on, with Joe Volk Speech (Box 3)
    - Neveshalom/Wahatal-Salam-an Oasis for Peace in the Middle East June 3, 2003 (Box 3)
    - "Women in War" by Jenny Matthews March 2, 2004 (Box 3)
    - "Electronic Voting & Voting Fraud" 12/6/2003 with Larry Kestenbaum (Box 3)
    - "The Violence of Occupation", a speech by Dr. Azmi Bishora, #819 (Box 3)
    - Literacy is Freedom 5/4/2004 (Box 3)
    - Veterans for Peace speak on Racism in the Military of the Anniversary of the Assassination of MLK. May 25 (Box 3)
    - Demonstration for Peace: One year Anniversary of the Iraq War, Part 2 6/1/2004 #822 (Box 3)
    - A Panel Discussion on Same-Sex Marriage, ACLU of Washtenaw County Annual Meeting (Box 3)
    - "The Courage to Refuse" An Israeli "Refusenik", Soldier & Stav Adivi's Message (Box 3)
    - "Winning Peace: Building a Movement That Will Succeed", a speech by Michael Albert, keynote speaker at the STOP THE WAR Conference, January 11-12 (Box 3)
    - "Risking Love in the Holy Land", #833 (Box 3)
    - "We Must Have Peace NOW!" May (Box 3)
    - Veterans Speak Against War, June (Box 3)
    - Our Other Prison System: U.S. Immigration Detention, June or July (Box 3)
    - "The U.S. Patriot Act Revisited in 2005" (Box 3)
    - Arlington West Master 11/20/2005 (Box 3)
    - "Counting Votes in Washtenaw County", WPA Program of 11/9/2005 (Box 3)
    - "Follow the Money in Michigan Politics", Rich Robinson, Director of Michigan Campaign Finance Network (Box 3)
    - Yes for Affirmative Action, No on the Civil Rights Initiative (Box 3)
    - "Thieves in High Places", also Ann Arbor Public Schools proposal, #836 8/24/2004 (Box 3)
    - "Dead Man Walking: The Story Continues, Sr. Helen Prejean (Box 3)
    - "Health Care of All Americans" Gray Panthers with Marjorie Mitchell 5/6/2006 (Box 3)
    - "Ballot Proposals 2006 (Box 3)
  - Other topics
    - Frontline, Economic Conversion, "Ashes of the Cold War" undated, 2 tapes (Box 4)
    - Patriot Act, with Mary Bajean undated (Box 4)
    - Secret Weapon; 3000 Common Ground; 4600 A City Council is my Rail II 6/4/1990 (Box 4)
    - Countering the "Threat of the Far Right, with June Rusten 11/1/1997 (Box 4)
    - The Washtenaw Coalition for the Living Wage 10/29/1998 (Box 4)
    - Justice for Sale, with Bill Moyers, PBS; Bermuda Triangle 11/23/1999 (Box 4)
    - Middle East with Libby Frank 12/3/2004 (Box 4)
    - "What I Learned about U.S. Foreign Policy" by Frank Dorrel, etc. 11/11/2005 (Box 4)
    - End of Oil, with Richard Porter 12/3/2005 (Box 4)
    - "Follow the Money that Controls MI Politics", Campaign Finance Update, with Richard Robinson 1/7/2006 (Box 4)
    - Minimum Wage 2/4/2006 (Box 4)